hello everyone welcome to a new session
in biochemistry
this presentation brings to you the
detailed account
of the metabolic process glycolysis
the glycolysis the term comes from two
greek terms
the greek root words which means sugar
or splitting okay sugar and splitting
which means glycolysis in nutshell it is
the
breakdown or the splitting or the
dissolution of
the sugar molecule it could be glucose
mainly it is glucose
okay so that is glycolysis so it can be
defined as
sequence of reactions that metabolizes
one molecule of glucose
to produce two molecules of spiderweight
along with production of atp
so uh the glucose molecule a single
glucose molecule
it is broken down to produce two
molecules of pyruvic acid
and along with that energy is produced
in the form of
atp molecules okay what are the
significant features of
what you call glycolysis you can say
that glycolysis
it occurs in all the cells of the body
and enzymes of enzymes required for the
glycolytic pathway
it is present in the cytoplasm of all
the cells
okay and it is considered to be the sole
source of
what you call energy in many of the
mammalian tissues and cell types for
example
glycolysis it is a major pathway for the
synthesis of energy for the
atp synthesis in tissues which lack
mitochondria
for example erythrocytes then
what you call cornea lens etc and other
than that
it is also the souls of souls of energy
in many
um tissues like renal medulla
of that of a brain sperm etc so
glycolysis is very essential for brain
which is depend upon uh glucose for
energy
and uh the as already mentioned the
glucose is the sole source of energy
in the brain and uh the like it depends
upon glycolysis for the complete
uh energy purpose and along with that
many anaerobic microorganisms they are
entirely dependent on
a glucose because glycolysis is a
anaerobic process
it doesn't require oxygen so it can
take place in the absence or
in the presence of oxygen
in the presence of oxygen that is in
aerobic condition what happens is
the glucose it breaks down to pyruvate
and this pyruvate later
it can ah get oxidized to carbon dioxide
and water
but in the absence of oxygen the um
like the glucose it will break down to
pyruvate which will enter the anaerobic
pathway
and result in the production of lactate
uh under anaerobic condition okay so
whichever will be the way
it we can see that uh it does it occurs
in the absence as well as in the
presence of oxygen
okay so that is more important thing
because there are plenty of organisms
which
come completely depend on the glycolytic
pathway for their energy
uh needs okay it is because glycolysis
can very well
uh get completed in the absence of
oxygen
now uh we can see that uh the
the glycolytic pathway it was
illustrated uh
or the complete uh pathway of glycolysis
was elucidated by 1940
and um endon and miroff they were two by
chemists
who had contributed uh to the knowledge
of
glycolysis um especially the enzymatic
uh breakdown at various stages of
glycolysis we completely studied
and elucidated by emden and meirav and
in honor of these two uh vacuums
the glycolysis is also known as emden
mayor of pathway
okay so the this is about the glycolysis
the interaction okay that is glycolysis
it involves sequence of reactions that
will convert
or break down glucose into two molecules
a single
molecule of glucose into two molecules
of uh pyruvic acid along with the
production of atp
okay and there are uh glycolysis is uh
unique because it can happen in both uh
presence or absence of oxygen
in the presence of oxygen the glucose
molecule it will be
broken down into two molecules of
pyruvate pyruvic acid
and uh under the in the absence of
oxygen this
pyruvic acid it can get converted into
lactic acid
okay uh in the uh um
or even what you call uh alcoholic
fermentation is that uh in
east and uh so uh in the presence of
oxygen what happens the pyruvate it is
getting oxidized to form carbon dioxide
water
right so it can happen in both
situations that are so
many cells which can which are
anaerobically functioning they do depend
on glycolysis for their
energy date secondly we can see that
there are many cells which
uh lack mitochondria they are they may
be aerobic but they lack mitochondria
so they have to depend upon glycolysis
for their
complete source of energy okay so that
is about the glycolysis
now regarding the um steps involved
glycolysis the whole complete sequence
of reactions it can be
divided into two phases that is
preparatory phase or the priming phase
we call
uh and the payoff phase okay the first
phase is a preparatory phase
and uh the first set of phases and the
preparatory phase or the first phase of
glycolysis
it is referred as priming phase or it is
known as energizing phase
okay priming phase in the sense the
phase where the energy is being utilized
okay energy is being utilized in the
form of atp right
and during this particular phase we can
see that the glucose
it gets uh phosphorylated uh
and then it splits into two uh
the triose phosphate molecules okay so
it is actually
uh glucose produ uh converted into
glyceraldehyde 3 phosphate
and this process it gets
included under preparatory phase and uh
the glyceraldehyde 3 phosphate is a
three carbon
containing compound or three carbon
containing sugar while glucose is a six
carbon containing sugar
so a six carbon sugar is uh converted
into
three carbon phosphorylated sugar okay
this is what happens in the preparatory
phase
and here you can see a
non-phosphorylated sugar is getting
converted into phosphorylated sugar
obviously there is a requirement of
atp okay so that is where the atp is
getting you
utilized and energy is uh like used
okay so it is actually glucose is
getting activated
or it is getting primed we call or it is
getting prepared for the
glycolytic process okay the second phase
uh actually it is known as the
payoff phase or we call it as uh energy
uh what you call um it
is actually atp is produced during this
phase okay it is energy conserving phase
okay or conservation phase okay
so here what happens is the free energy
which is trapped in the substrate
molecules
uh it is the free energy it is getting
trapped in the substrate molecules and
this
is getting con conserved in the form of
atp okay
here the glyceraldehyde three phosphate
it is getting converted into
the pyruvic acid okay ultimately passing
through various tips
pyruvic acid is produced and during the
this particular phase
nadh in atp molecules are produced
uh which is actually energy conserving
molecules
okay so glycolysis it is for um the
whole set of reactions it can be
uh differentiated into two phases
preparatory phase and p
of phase preparatory phase is otherwise
known as priming phase or energy
spending phase okay it is actually
energy requiring phase
here what happens is the glucose uh
molecule is getting prepared
or activated to undergo the glycolytic
pathway
okay and in the preparatory phase
glucose which is a six carbon sugar is
getting converted into
phosphorylated three carbon sugar which
is this glyceraldehyde three phosphate
okay during the pair phase this
phosphorylated three carbon sugar is
getting converted into pyruvic acid
through various steps and during these
phase we can see that
uh like energy molecules atp and 88 etc
they are being produced
okay so it is an energy conserving uh
phase or we can say
during this phase energy is generated
okay so preparatory phase of priming
phase energy
utilization phase or energizing phase
while
um the payoff phase that is the energy
generation phase okay so this is about
the
two major phases of glycolysis we can
see the phase wise
glycolithic what all are the reactions
going on okay